<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-19T15:56:58+01:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Hidden Histories</title><subtitle>Digital Humanities 1949 - Present</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Influence of Algorithmic Thinking: Judy Malloy and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/judy-malloy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Influence of Algorithmic Thinking: Judy Malloy and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2015-08-11T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-08-11T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/judy-malloy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/judy-malloy">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_7&quot;&gt;Chapter 7 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was carried out via skype on 11 August 2015 at 20:30 GMT. Malloy was provided with the core interview questions in advance. Here she recalls that after graduating from university she took a job as a searcher/editor for the National Union Catalog of the Library of Congress. About a year after she arrived Henriette D. Avram began work on the process of devising a way to make the library’s cataloguing information machine readable (work that would ultimately lead to the development of the MARC format (Schudel 2006)). Malloy recalls this wider context as her first encounter, of sorts, with computing technology: though she did not participate in that work it made a clear impression on her. She had learned to programme in FORTRAN in the 1960s when working as a technical librarian at the Ball Brothers Research Corporation. She had also held other technical roles at Electromagnetic Research Corp and with a contractor for the Goddard Space Flight Center, which was computerising its library around the time she worked there. She recalls that she did not use computers in her artistic work until the 1980s (when she bought an Apple II for her son). However, she had been working in an interactive, multimedia and associative mode for some time before then, as evidenced by the card catalog poetry and electronic books that she created in the 1970s and early 1980s. In this interview she traces the importance of card catalogs, Systems Analysis and algorithmic thinking to many aspects of her work. She also reflects on why it was that the idea of combining computing and literature did not occur to her (and also was not practically feasible) until a later stage in her career. Among other topics, she reflects on the kinds of computing and computing environments that she encountered, from the reactions in the 1960s of some male engineers to the presence of a female technical librarian in the mainframe room to the thrill of discovering the community that was connected via the Whole Earth ‘Lectronic Link (The WELL).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Judy Malloy</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 7 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The University Was Still Taking Account of universitas scientiarum: Wilhelm Ott and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/wilhelm-ott" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The University Was Still Taking Account of universitas scientiarum: Wilhelm Ott and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2015-07-14T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-07-14T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/wilhelm-ott</id><content type="html" xml:base="/wilhelm-ott">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_4&quot;&gt;Chapter 4 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/40&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further related blog posts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/246&quot;&gt;related blog post&lt;/a&gt; written by Julianne Nyhan&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This oral history interview between Wilhelm Ott and Julianne Nyhan was carried out on 14 July 2015, shortly after 10am, in the offices of pagina in Tübingen, Germany. Ott was provided with the core questions in advance of the interview. He recalls that his earliest contact with computing was in 1966 when he took an introductory programming course in the Deutsches Rechenzentrum (German Computing Center) in Darmstadt. Having become slightly bored with the exercises that attendees of the course were asked to complete he began working on programmes to aid his metrical analysis of Latin hexameters, a project he would continue to work on for the next 19 years. After completing the course in Darmstadt he approached, among others such as IBM, the Classics Department at Tübingen University to gauge their interest in his emerging expertise. Though there was no tradition in the Department of applying computing to philological problems they quickly grasped the significance and potential of such approaches. Fortunately, this happened just when the computing center, up to then part of the Institute for Mathematics, was transformed into a central service unit for the university. Drawing on initial funding from the Physics department a position was created for Ott in the Tübingen Computing Center. His role was to pursue his Latin hexameters project and, above all, to provide specialised support for computer applications in the Humanities. In this interview Ott recalls a number of the early projects that he supported such as the concordance to the Vulgate that was undertaken by Bonifatius Fischer, along with the assistance they received from Roberto Busa when it came to lemmatisation. He also talks at length about the context in which his TUSTEP programme came about and its subsequent development. The interview strikes a slightly wistful tone as he recalls the University of Tübingen’s embrace of the notion of universitas scientiarum in the 1960s and contrasts this with the rather more precarious position of the Humanities in many countries today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Nyhan, J. (2017, July). The University was still taking account of universitas scientiarum: Wilhelm Ott [Billet]. Retrieved 19 June 2018, from https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/246&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wilhelm Ott</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 4 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Hidden Histories</title><link href="/welcome" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Hidden Histories" /><published>2015-07-02T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-07-02T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="/welcome">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hidden Histories is a research project into the application of computational methods to the humanities during the period from 1949 to the present. The project conducts, collects and disseminates interviews with scholars and practitioners who were active during this period. Combining the interviews with archival data, new insight is gained into the emergence of a field known today as &lt;em&gt;digital humanities&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely accepted that the application of computational methods to the humanities can be traced back to at least 1949, when Roberto Busa envisaged an index variorum of some 11 million words of medieval Latin in the works of Thomas Aquinas and related authors. Notes and contributions towards a history of the computer in the humanities have appeared in recent years; however, our understanding of such developments remains incomplete and largely unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project gathers and makes available sources that enable the investigation of the social, intellectual and cultural context that shaped the earliest applications of computing to the humanities. It is from this context that the title ‘Hidden Histories’ derives because, for the most part, such information can not be gleaned from extant documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is interdisciplinary in its methodology and draws on oral history, digital humanities and cultural studies. With the aim of capturing memories, observations and insights that are rarely recorded in the scholarly literature of the field, the project conducts interviews with scholars and practitioners who applied computational methods to the humanities in the age of mainframe computing to the present day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An introduction to the Hidden Histories project is available as an &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqt044&quot;&gt;open access article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: “No. 0243,” Hidden Histories: Digital Humanities 1949 – Present, accessed June 17, 2018, http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/24.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Julianne Nyhan</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Hidden Histories is a research project into the application of computational methods to the humanities during the period from 1949 to the present. The project conducts, collects and disseminates interviews with scholars and practitioners who were active during this period. Combining the interviews with archival data, new insight is gained into the emergence of a field known today as digital humanities.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">hic Rhodus, hic salta: Tito Orlandi and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/tito-orlandi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="hic Rhodus, hic salta: Tito Orlandi and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2014-10-17T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-10-17T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/tito-orlandi</id><content type="html" xml:base="/tito-orlandi">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_5&quot;&gt;Chapter 5 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further related blog posts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/251&quot;&gt;related blog post&lt;/a&gt; written by Julianne Nyhan&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This oral history interview between Wilhelm Ott and Julianne Nyhan was carried out on 14 July 2015, shortly after 10am, in the offices of pagina in Tübingen, Germany. Ott was provided with the core questions in advance of the interview. He recalls that his earliest contact with computing was in 1966 when he took an introductory programming course in the Deutsches Rechenzentrum (German Computing Center) in Darmstadt. Having become slightly bored with the exercises that attendees of the course were asked to complete he began working on programmes to aid his metrical analysis of Latin hexameters, a project he would continue to work on for the next 19 years. After completing the course in Darmstadt he approached, among others such as IBM, the Classics Department at Tübingen University to gauge their interest in his emerging expertise. Though there was no tradition in the Department of applying computing to philological problems they quickly grasped the significance and potential of such approaches. Fortunately, this happened just when the computing center, up to then part of the Institute for Mathematics, was transformed into a central service unit for the university. Drawing on initial funding from the Physics department a position was created for Ott in the Tübingen Computing Center. His role was to pursue his Latin hexameters project and, above all, to provide specialised support for computer applications in the Humanities. In this interview Ott recalls a number of the early projects that he supported such as the concordance to the Vulgate that was undertaken by Bonifatius Fischer, along with the assistance they received from Roberto Busa when it came to lemmatisation. He also talks at length about the context in which his TUSTEP programme came about and its subsequent development. The interview strikes a slightly wistful tone as he recalls the University of Tübingen’s embrace of the notion of universitas scientiarum in the 1960s and contrasts this with the rather more precarious position of the Humanities in many countries today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Nyhan, J. (2014, October). hic Rhodus, hic salta: Tito Orlandi [Billet]. Retrieved 19 June 2018, from https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/251&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tito Orlandi</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 5 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">They Took a Chance: Susan Hockey and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/susan-hockey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="They Took a Chance: Susan Hockey and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2013-06-21T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-06-21T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/susan-hockey</id><content type="html" xml:base="/susan-hockey">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_6&quot;&gt;Chapter 6 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;https://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/admin/items/show/44&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further related blog posts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/264&quot;&gt;related blog post&lt;/a&gt; written by Julianne Nyhan&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was carried out via Skype on 21 June 2013. Hockey was provided with the core questions in advance of the interview. Here she recalls how her interest in Humanities Computing was piqued by the articles that Andrew Morton published in the Observer in the 1960s about his work on the authorship of the Pauline Epistles. She went on to secure a position in the Atlas Computer Laboratory where she was an advisor on COCOA version 2 and wrote software for the electronic display of Arabic and other non-ASCII characters. The Atlas Computer Laboratory was funded by the Science Research Council and provided computing support for universities and researchers across the UK. While there she benefitted from access to the journal CHum and built connections with the emerging Humanities Computing community through events she attended starting with the ‘Symposium on Uses of the Computer in Literary Research’ organised by Roy Wisbey in Cambridge in 1970 (probably the earliest such meeting in the UK). Indeed, she emphasises the importance that such gatherings played in the formation of the discipline. As well as discussing her contribution to organisations like ALLC and TEI she recalls those who particularly influenced her such as, inter alia, Roberto Busa and Antonio Zampolli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Susan Hockey. (n.d.). Retrieved 16 June 2018, from http://www.chilton-computing.org.uk/acl/associates/permanent/hockey.htm&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Susan Hockey</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 6 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Individuation Is There in All the Different Strata: John Burrows, Hugh Craig and Willard McCarty</title><link href="/john-burrows-hugh-craig" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Individuation Is There in All the Different Strata: John Burrows, Hugh Craig and Willard McCarty" /><published>2013-06-04T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-06-04T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/john-burrows-hugh-craig</id><content type="html" xml:base="/john-burrows-hugh-craig">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_3&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;, Chapter 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/39&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This oral history interview between Willard McCarty (on behalf of Julianne Nyhan), John Burrows and Hugh Craig took place on 4 June 2013 at the University of Newcastle, Australia. Harold Short (Professor of Humanities Computing at King’s College London and a Visiting Professor at the University of Western Sydney in the School of Computing, Engineering and Mathematics) was also present for much of the interview. Burrows recounts that his first encounter with computing took place in the late 1970s, via John Lambert, who was then the Director of the University of Newcastle’s Computing Service. Burrows had sought Lambert out when the card-indexes of common words that he had been compiling became too difficult and too numerous to manage. Craig’s first contact was in the mid-1980s, after Burrows put him in charge of a project that used a Remington word processor. At many points in the interview Burrows and Craig reflect on the substantial amount of time, and, indeed, belief, that they invested not only in the preparation of texts for analysis but also in the learning and development of new processes and techniques (often drawn from disciplines outside English Literature). Much is said about the wider social contexts of such processes: Craig, for example, reflects on the sense of possibility and purposefulness that having Burrows as a colleague helped to create for him. Indeed, he wonders whether he would have had the confidence to invest the time and effort that he did had he been elsewhere. Burrows emphasises the network of formal and informal, national and international expertise that he benefitted from, for example, John Dawson in Cambridge and Susan Hockey in Oxford. So too they reflect on the positive results that the scepticism they sometimes encountered had on their work. As central as computing has been to their research lives they emphasise that their main aim was to study literature and continuing to publish in core literature journals (in addition to DH journals) has been an important aspect of this. Though they used techniques and models that are also used by Linguists and Statisticians their focus has remained on questioning rather than answering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;John Burrows Award. (2014, October 13). Retrieved 19 June 2018, from http://dh2015.org/john-burrows-award/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hugh Craig. (2015, January 16). Retrieved 19 June 2018, from https://www.newcastle.edu.au/profile/hugh-craig&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>John Burrows, Hugh Craig</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Computation and the Humanities, Chapter 3</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Postmodern Culture and More: an Oral History Conversation between John Unsworth and Anne Welsh</title><link href="/john-unsworth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Postmodern Culture and More: an Oral History Conversation between John Unsworth and Anne Welsh" /><published>2012-06-01T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-06-01T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/john-unsworth</id><content type="html" xml:base="/john-unsworth">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000132/000132.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000132/resources/audio/john_unsworth.MP3&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Unsworth recounts that he first became involved with computing in the Humanities c. 1989 as a new faculty member at North Carolina State University where he was hired to teach post-World War II American literature. He and his colleagues wanted to set up a new journal as only one other journal existed in that area. They were introduced to the recently released LISTSERV software and the first issue of the journal was circulated on email lists and bulletin boards. It was called Postmodern Culture and twenty-two years later is still published by Johns Hopkins University Press. It was the first peer-reviewed electronic journal in the Humanities; nevertheless, not all senior colleagues were in favour of it and, as a junior faculty member, his participation in it. He recounts that was not able to avail of formal training in computing but he did have technical knowledge of computing, mostly picked up while procrastinating on this PhD. By the early 1990s he was reading Humanist and attending conferences that focused on electronic journals where he encountered a range of academic and non-academic projects. In 1993 he moved to the University of Virginia where he directed the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities (IATH). He reflects on the wide range of people and projects that he worked with and that it was around this time that he became involved with the community now known as digital humanities. He reflects in detail on the first digital humanities conference he attended in Paris in 1994 and concludes by discussing some of the changes that the advent of the Web has heralded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: John Unsworth. (n.d.). Retrieved 19 June 2018, from https://ischool.illinois.edu/people/faculty/unsworth&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>John Unsworth</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Digital Humanities Quarterly</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Collaboration Must Be Fundamental or It’s Not Going to Work”: an Oral History Conversation between Harold Short and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/harold-short" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Collaboration Must Be Fundamental or It's Not Going to Work”: an Oral History Conversation between Harold Short and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2012-06-01T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-06-01T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/harold-short</id><content type="html" xml:base="/harold-short">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000133/000133.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000133/resources/audio/harold_short.MP3&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harold Short recounts that his interest in Computing and the Humanities goes back to when he was an undergraduate in English and French at a university in the former Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe). There, whilst undertaking summer work in the library, he saw first-hand the potential of digital methods. After arriving in London in 1972 he took an Open University degree in mathematics, computing and systems. Among his early influences he identifies the reading he did on matters related to cognitive science whilst undertaking a postgraduate certificated in education. In the UK he worked at the BBC as programmer, systems analyst and then systems manager. In 1988 he moved to King’s College London to take up the post of Assistant Director in Computing Services for Humanities and Information Management. One of his first tasks was to work with the Humanities Faculty to develop an undergraduate programme in humanities and computing. The first digital humanities conference he attended was the first joint international conference of ALLC and ACH, held at the University Toronto in 1989, which c. 450 people attended. He reflects on aspects of the institutional shape of the field towards the end of the 1980s, including the key Centres that existed then, the first meeting of the Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing (ALLC) and those who were active in it such as Roy Wisbey, Susan Hockey and the late Antonio Zampolli. He gives a detailed discussion of the development of what is now the Department of Digital Humanities in King’s College London, both in terms of the administrative and institutional issues involved, as well as the intellectual. He also reflects on some of the most successful collaborations that the Department has been involved in, for example, the AHRC funded Henry III Fine Rolls project, and the conditions and working practices that characterised them. He closes by discussing his impressions about the movement of scholars into and out of the discipline and of the institutional issues that have had an impact on digital humanities centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Harold Short - Research Portal, King’s College, London. (n.d.). Retrieved 17 June 2018, from https://kclpure.kcl.ac.uk/portal/en/persons/harold-short(0426328d-ff7b-4536-aeff-6cebdbebbecc).html&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harold Short</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Digital Humanities Quarterly</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trading Stories: an Oral History Conversation between Geoffrey Rockwell and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/geoffrey-rockwell" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trading Stories: an Oral History Conversation between Geoffrey Rockwell and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2012-04-28T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-04-28T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/geoffrey-rockwell</id><content type="html" xml:base="/geoffrey-rockwell">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000135/000135.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000135/resources/audio/geoffrey_rockwell.MP3&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extended interview with Geoffrey Rockwell was carried out via Skype on the 28th April 2012. He narrates that he had been aware of computing developments when growing up in Italy but it was in college in the late 1970s that he took formal training in computing. He bought his first computer, an Apple II clone, after graduation when he was working as a teacher in the Middle East. Throughout the interview he reflects on the various computers he has used and how the mouse that he used with an early Macintosh instinctively appealed to him. By the mid-1980s he was attending graduate school in the University of Toronto and was accepted on to the Apple Research Partnership Programme, which enabled him to be embedded in the central University of Toronto Computing Services; he went on to hold a full time position there. Also taking a PhD in Philosophy, he spent many lunch times talking with John Bradley. This resulted in the building of text analysis tools and their application to Hume’s Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion, as well as some of the earliest, if not the earliest, conference paper on visualisation in the digital humanities community. He reflects on the wide range of influences that shaped and inspired his early work in the field, for example, the Research Computing Group at the University of Toronto and their work in visual programming environments. In 1994 he applied, and was hired at McMaster University to what he believes was the first job openly advertised as a humanities computing position in Canada. After exploring the opposition to computing that he encountered he reflects that the image of the underdog has perhaps become a foundational myth of digital humanities and questions whether it is still a useful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Advancing digital literacy in an era of big data | Work of Arts. (2017, July 10). Retrieved 16 June 2018, from https://www.woablog.com/2017/07/advancing-digital-literacy-in-an-era-of-big-data/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Digital Humanities Quarterly</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Questioning, Asking and Enduring Curiosity: an Oral History Conversation between Julianne Nyhan and Willard McCarty</title><link href="/willard-mccarty" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questioning, Asking and Enduring Curiosity: an Oral History Conversation between Julianne Nyhan and Willard McCarty" /><published>2012-03-27T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-03-27T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/willard-mccarty</id><content type="html" xml:base="/willard-mccarty">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000134/000134.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000134/resources/audio/willard_mccarty.MP3&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was carried out with Willard McCarty on Tuesday 27th March, 2012 in University College London. He recounts that his earliest encounter with computing was in the Lawrence Radiation Laboratory in Berkley where he worked with semi-automated scanning equipment for the Alvarez high-energy physics projects. After his dreams of becoming a physicist were thwarted he transferred to Reed College. There he did not have the opportunity to take formal training in computing; for the most part, Computer Science departments did not exist then. So, he learned to programme “on the job” with help from a talented physicist turned computer programmer named Bill Gates (no association with Microsoft). His first encounter with what we now call digital humanities was at the University of Toronto where he worked on the Records of Early English Drama project whilst undertaking a PhD on 17th century non-dramatic poetry. In 1984/5, as he was finishing his PhD, he accepted an academic support role at the Centre for Computing in the Humanities at Toronto, where he remained until 1996 when he accepted an academic post in King’s College London. In Toronto he was keenly aware of the staff-faculty divide and the marginalised position of those who used computers in Humanities research. Nevertheless, the opportunities that the role brought to meet with a range of scholars interested in computing had a lasting influence on him. So too, with funding from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada he was able to undertake a research project on Ovid’s Metamorphosis. He closes the interview by reflecting on his early involvement with the conference scene and people who have influenced him, from academics to his calligraphy teacher Lloyd Reynolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Bern (2014, January 29). Retrieved 16 June 2018, from http://www.mccarty.org.uk/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>willard</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Digital Humanities Quarterly</summary></entry></feed>