<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-07-16T20:16:35+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Hidden Histories</title><subtitle>Digital Humanities 1949 - Present</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Podcasts of Symposium on Methodologies for the History of Computing in the Humanities, c.1949-1980 now available!</title><link href="/symposium-on-methodologies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podcasts of Symposium on Methodologies for the History of Computing in the Humanities, c.1949-1980 now available!" /><published>2018-06-17T10:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-17T10:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/symposium-on-methodologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="/symposium-on-methodologies">&lt;p&gt;University College London, 17 September 2011
(Sponsored by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hkfz.uni-trier.de/?&amp;amp;sel_id=1&quot;&gt;HKFZ&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/dh/&quot;&gt;UCLDH&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Click the titles to listen to the podcasts.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;opening-keynote--beyond-chronology-and-profession-discovering-how-to-write-a-history-of-the-digital-humanities&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/11&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opening Keynote&lt;/strong&gt; : Beyond chronology and profession: discovering how to write a history of the Digital Humanities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willard McCarty, Department of Digital Humanities, King’s College London; Centre for Cultural Research, University of Western Sydney.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;knowledge-spaces-and-digital-humanities&quot;&gt;Knowledge Spaces and Digital Humanities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claudine Moulin, Universitaet Trier, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unwriting-the-history-of-humanities-computing&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/10&quot;&gt;Unwriting the history of Humanities Computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Vanhoutte, Royal Academy of Dutch Language and Literature - Ghent, Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;crowd-sourcing-beyond-the-traditional-boundaries-of-academic-history&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/9&quot;&gt;Crowd sourcing: beyond the traditional, boundaries of academic history&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Melissa Terras, Dept. Information Studies, UCL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;different-stories-to-be-lived-and-told-recovering-lehmann-james-oppenheimer-1868-1916-for-the-narrative-of-the-irish-arts--crafts-movement-1894-1925&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/12&quot;&gt;Different stories to be lived and told: recovering Lehmann James Oppenheimer (1868-1916) for the narrative of the Irish Arts &amp;amp; Crafts movement (1894-1925)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James G.R. Cronin, School of History &amp;amp; Centre for Adult Continuing Education, University College Cork, Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;oral-history-and-acts-of-recovery-humanizing-history&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/6&quot;&gt;Oral History and acts of recovery: humanizing history?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Flinn, Dept. Information Studies, UCL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lost-origins-of-information-science&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/7&quot;&gt;Lost origins of Information Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanda Broughton, Dept. Information Studies, UCL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dh-pioneers-and-progeny-some-reflections-on-generational-accomplishment-and-engagement-in-the-digital-humanities&quot;&gt;DH pioneers and progeny: some reflections on generational accomplishment and engagement in the Digital Humanities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray Siemens, Faculty of Humanities, University of Victoria. (Virtual presentation)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;closing-keynote-data-vs-text-forty-years-of-confrontation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/8&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Closing Keynote&lt;/strong&gt;: Data vs. Text: forty years of confrontation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lou Burnard, Oxford University Computing Services (Emeritus).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;discussion-towards-an-oral-history-of-computing-in-the-humanities-chaired-by-anne-welsh-and-julianne-nyhan-dept-information-studies-ucl&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion&lt;/strong&gt;: towards an oral history of Computing in the Humanities, Chaired by Anne Welsh and Julianne Nyhan, Dept. Information Studies, UCL&lt;/h4&gt;</content><author><name>Julianne Nyhan</name></author><category term="activities" /><category term="talks" /><summary type="html">University College London, 17 September 2011 (Sponsored by HKFZ and UCLDH)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Influence of Algorithmic Thinking: Judy Malloy and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/judy-malloy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Influence of Algorithmic Thinking: Judy Malloy and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2015-08-11T10:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-08-11T10:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/judy-malloy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/judy-malloy">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_7&quot;&gt;Chapter 7 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was carried out via skype on 11 August 2015 at 20:30 GMT. Malloy was provided with the core interview questions in advance. Here she recalls that after graduating from university she took a job as a searcher/editor for the National Union Catalog of the Library of Congress. About a year after she arrived Henriette D. Avram began work on the process of devising a way to make the library’s cataloguing information machine readable (work that would ultimately lead to the development of the MARC format (Schudel 2006)). Malloy recalls this wider context as her first encounter, of sorts, with computing technology: though she did not participate in that work it made a clear impression on her. She had learned to programme in FORTRAN in the 1960s when working as a technical librarian at the Ball Brothers Research Corporation. She had also held other technical roles at Electromagnetic Research Corp and with a contractor for the Goddard Space Flight Center, which was computerising its library around the time she worked there. She recalls that she did not use computers in her artistic work until the 1980s (when she bought an Apple II for her son). However, she had been working in an interactive, multimedia and associative mode for some time before then, as evidenced by the card catalog poetry and electronic books that she created in the 1970s and early 1980s. In this interview she traces the importance of card catalogs, Systems Analysis and algorithmic thinking to many aspects of her work. She also reflects on why it was that the idea of combining computing and literature did not occur to her (and also was not practically feasible) until a later stage in her career. Among other topics, she reflects on the kinds of computing and computing environments that she encountered, from the reactions in the 1960s of some male engineers to the presence of a female technical librarian in the mainframe room to the thrill of discovering the community that was connected via the Whole Earth ‘Lectronic Link (The WELL).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Judy Malloy</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 7 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The University Was Still Taking Account of universitas scientiarum: Wilhelm Ott and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/wilhelm-ott" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The University Was Still Taking Account of universitas scientiarum: Wilhelm Ott and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2015-07-14T10:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-07-14T10:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/wilhelm-ott</id><content type="html" xml:base="/wilhelm-ott">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_4&quot;&gt;Chapter 4 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/40&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further related blog posts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/246&quot;&gt;related blog post&lt;/a&gt; written by Julianne Nyhan&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This oral history interview between Wilhelm Ott and Julianne Nyhan was carried out on 14 July 2015, shortly after 10am, in the offices of pagina in Tübingen, Germany. Ott was provided with the core questions in advance of the interview. He recalls that his earliest contact with computing was in 1966 when he took an introductory programming course in the Deutsches Rechenzentrum (German Computing Center) in Darmstadt. Having become slightly bored with the exercises that attendees of the course were asked to complete he began working on programmes to aid his metrical analysis of Latin hexameters, a project he would continue to work on for the next 19 years. After completing the course in Darmstadt he approached, among others such as IBM, the Classics Department at Tübingen University to gauge their interest in his emerging expertise. Though there was no tradition in the Department of applying computing to philological problems they quickly grasped the significance and potential of such approaches. Fortunately, this happened just when the computing center, up to then part of the Institute for Mathematics, was transformed into a central service unit for the university. Drawing on initial funding from the Physics department a position was created for Ott in the Tübingen Computing Center. His role was to pursue his Latin hexameters project and, above all, to provide specialised support for computer applications in the Humanities. In this interview Ott recalls a number of the early projects that he supported such as the concordance to the Vulgate that was undertaken by Bonifatius Fischer, along with the assistance they received from Roberto Busa when it came to lemmatisation. He also talks at length about the context in which his TUSTEP programme came about and its subsequent development. The interview strikes a slightly wistful tone as he recalls the University of Tübingen’s embrace of the notion of universitas scientiarum in the 1960s and contrasts this with the rather more precarious position of the Humanities in many countries today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Nyhan, J. (2017, July). The University was still taking account of universitas scientiarum: Wilhelm Ott [Billet]. Retrieved 19 June 2018, from https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/246&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wilhelm Ott</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 4 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Hidden Histories</title><link href="/welcome" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Hidden Histories" /><published>2015-07-02T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-07-02T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="/welcome">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hidden Histories is a research project into the application of computational methods to the humanities during the period from 1949 to the present. The project conducts, collects and disseminates interviews with scholars and practitioners who were active during this period. Combining the interviews with archival data, new insight is gained into the emergence of a field known today as &lt;em&gt;digital humanities&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely accepted that the application of computational methods to the humanities can be traced back to at least 1949, when Roberto Busa envisaged an index variorum of some 11 million words of medieval Latin in the works of Thomas Aquinas and related authors. Notes and contributions towards a history of the computer in the humanities have appeared in recent years; however, our understanding of such developments remains incomplete and largely unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project gathers and makes available sources that enable the investigation of the social, intellectual and cultural context that shaped the earliest applications of computing to the humanities. It is from this context that the title ‘Hidden Histories’ derives because, for the most part, such information can not be gleaned from extant documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is interdisciplinary in its methodology and draws on oral history, digital humanities and cultural studies. With the aim of capturing memories, observations and insights that are rarely recorded in the scholarly literature of the field, the project conducts interviews with scholars and practitioners who applied computational methods to the humanities in the age of mainframe computing to the present day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An introduction to the Hidden Histories project is available as an &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqt044&quot;&gt;open access article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Busa Archive #0614. All photos are reproduced here with the permission of the Università Cattolica Library Archives, Milan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Julianne Nyhan</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Hidden Histories is a research project into the application of computational methods to the humanities during the period from 1949 to the present. The project conducts, collects and disseminates interviews with scholars and practitioners who were active during this period. Combining the interviews with archival data, new insight is gained into the emergence of a field known today as digital humanities.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Would Think of Myself as Sitting Inside the Computer: Mary Dee Harris and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/mary-dee-harris" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Would Think of Myself as Sitting Inside the Computer: Mary Dee Harris and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2015-06-03T10:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-06-03T10:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/mary-dee-harris</id><content type="html" xml:base="/mary-dee-harris">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_8&quot;&gt;Chapter 8 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/admin/items/show/41&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This oral history interview was conducted on 3 June 2015 via Skype. Harris was provided with the interview questions in advance. Here she recalls her early encounters with computing, including her work at the Jet Propulsion Lab in Pasadena, California. Despite these early encounters with computing she had planned to leave it behind when she returned to graduate school to pursue a PhD; however, the discovery of c.200 pages of a Dylan Thomas manuscript prompted her to rethink this. Her graduate study was based in the English Department of the University of Texas at Austin, which did not have an account with the computer centre, and so it was necessary for her to apply for a graduate student grant in order to buy computer time. Her PhD studies convinced her of the merits of using computers in literary research and she hoped to convince her colleagues of this too. However, her applications for academic jobs were not initially successful. After working in Industry for a time she went on to secure academic positions in Computer Science at various universities. During her career she also held a number of posts in Industry and as a Consultant. In these roles she worked on a wide range of Artificial Intelligence and especially Natural Language Processing projects. Her interview is a wide-ranging one. She reflects on topics like the peripheral position of a number of those who worked in Humanities Computing in the 1970s and her personal reactions to some of the computing systems she used, for example, the IBM 360. She also recalls how she, as a woman, was sometimes treated in what tended to be a male-dominated sector, for example, the Physics Professor who asked “So are you going to be my little girl?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Mary Dee’s Life Story. (n.d.). Retrieved 20 June 2018, from https://marydeewordpresscom.wordpress.com/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mary Dee Harris</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 8 of Computation and the Humanities Audio version: accompanying audio interview</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">hic Rhodus, hic salta: Tito Orlandi and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/tito-orlandi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="hic Rhodus, hic salta: Tito Orlandi and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2014-10-17T10:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-10-17T10:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/tito-orlandi</id><content type="html" xml:base="/tito-orlandi">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_5&quot;&gt;Chapter 5 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further related blog posts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/251&quot;&gt;related blog post&lt;/a&gt; written by Julianne Nyhan&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This oral history interview between Wilhelm Ott and Julianne Nyhan was carried out on 14 July 2015, shortly after 10am, in the offices of pagina in Tübingen, Germany. Ott was provided with the core questions in advance of the interview. He recalls that his earliest contact with computing was in 1966 when he took an introductory programming course in the Deutsches Rechenzentrum (German Computing Center) in Darmstadt. Having become slightly bored with the exercises that attendees of the course were asked to complete he began working on programmes to aid his metrical analysis of Latin hexameters, a project he would continue to work on for the next 19 years. After completing the course in Darmstadt he approached, among others such as IBM, the Classics Department at Tübingen University to gauge their interest in his emerging expertise. Though there was no tradition in the Department of applying computing to philological problems they quickly grasped the significance and potential of such approaches. Fortunately, this happened just when the computing center, up to then part of the Institute for Mathematics, was transformed into a central service unit for the university. Drawing on initial funding from the Physics department a position was created for Ott in the Tübingen Computing Center. His role was to pursue his Latin hexameters project and, above all, to provide specialised support for computer applications in the Humanities. In this interview Ott recalls a number of the early projects that he supported such as the concordance to the Vulgate that was undertaken by Bonifatius Fischer, along with the assistance they received from Roberto Busa when it came to lemmatisation. He also talks at length about the context in which his TUSTEP programme came about and its subsequent development. The interview strikes a slightly wistful tone as he recalls the University of Tübingen’s embrace of the notion of universitas scientiarum in the 1960s and contrasts this with the rather more precarious position of the Humanities in many countries today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Nyhan, J. (2014, October). hic Rhodus, hic salta: Tito Orlandi [Billet]. Retrieved 19 June 2018, from https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/251&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tito Orlandi</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 5 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting Computers into Humanists’ Thinking: John Bradley and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/john-bradley" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Computers into Humanists’ Thinking: John Bradley and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2014-09-09T10:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-09-09T10:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/john-bradley</id><content type="html" xml:base="/john-bradley">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_14&quot;&gt;Chapter 14 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/admin/items/show/48&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview took place in Bradley’s office in Drury Lane, King’s College London on 9 September 2014 around 11:30. Bradley was provided with the interview questions in advance. He recalls that his interest in computing started in the early 1960s. As computer time was not then available to him he sometimes wrote out in longhand the FORTRAN code he was beginning to learn from books. One of his earliest encounters with Humanities Computing was the concordance to Diodorus Siculus that he programmed in the late 1970s. The printed concordance that resulted filled the back of a station wagon. The burgeoning Humanities Computing community in Toronto at that time collaborated both with the University of Toronto Computer Services Department (where Bradley was based) and the Centre for Computing in the Humanities, founded by Ian Lancashire. Aware of the small but significant interest in text analysis that existed in Toronto at that time and pondering the implications of the shift from batch to interactive computing he began work as a developer of Text Analysis Computing Tools (TACT). He also recalls his later work on Pliny, a personal note management system, and how it was at least partly undertaken in response to the lack of engagement with computational text analysis he noted among Humanists. In addition to other themes, he reflects at various points during the interview on models of partnership between Academic and Technical experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: King’s College London - John Bradley. (n.d.). Retrieved 21 June 2018, from https://www.kcl.ac.uk/artshums/depts/ddh/people/emeritus/bradley/index.aspx&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>John Bradley</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 14 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moderate Expectations, Tolerable Disappointments: Claus Huitfeldt and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/claus-huitfeldt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moderate Expectations, Tolerable Disappointments: Claus Huitfeldt and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2014-07-11T10:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-07-11T10:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/claus-huitfeldt</id><content type="html" xml:base="/claus-huitfeldt">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_15&quot;&gt;Chapter 15 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/admin/items/show/42&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was conducted on 11 July at the 2014 Digital Humanities Conference, Lausanne, Switzerland. Huitfeldt recounts that he first encountered computing at the beginning of the 1980s via the Institute of Continental Shelf Research when he was a Philosophy student at the University of Trondheim. However, it was in connection with a Humanities project on the writings of Wittgenstein that he learned to programme. When that project closed he worked as a computing consultant in the Norwegian Computing Center for the Humanities and in 1990 he established a new project called the ‘Wittgenstein Archives’, which aimed to prepare and publish a machine-readable version of Wittgenstein’s Nachlass. Here he discusses the context in which he began working on the encoding scheme (A Multi-Element Code System) that he developed for that project. The influence of MECS went beyond the Wittgenstein Archives. According to Ore (2014) ‘when XML itself was under development, the idea of well-formed documents (as different from documents valid according to a DTD or schema) was taken into XML from MECS’. In addition to discussing matters like the trajectory of DH research and his early encounters with the conference community he also discusses some of the fundamental issues that interest him like the role of technology in relation to the written word and the lack of engagement of the Philosophy community with such questions. Ultimately he concludes that he does not view DH as a discipline, but rather as a reconfiguration of the academic landscape as a result of the convergence of tools and methods within and between the Humanities and other disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Claus Huitfeldt. (n.d.). Retrieved 21 June 2018, from https://www.uib.no/en/persons/Claus.Huitfeldt&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Claus Huitfeldt</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 15 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Mourned the University for a Long Time: Michael Sperberg-McQueen and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/michael-sperberg-mcqueen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Mourned the University for a Long Time: Michael Sperberg-McQueen and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2014-07-09T10:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-07-09T10:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/michael-sperberg-mcqueen</id><content type="html" xml:base="/michael-sperberg-mcqueen">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_12&quot;&gt;Chapter 12 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/admin/items/show/47&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview took place on 9 July 2014 at dh2014, the Digital Humanities Conference that was held in Lausanne, Switzerland that year. In it Sperberg-McQueen recalls having had some exposure to programming in 1967, as a 13 year-old. His next notable encounter with computing was as a graduate student when he set about using computers to make a bibliography of secondary literature on the Elder Edda. His earliest encounters with Humanities Computing were via books, and he mentions the proceedings of the ‘Concordances and the Dictionary of Old English’ conference and a book by Susan Hockey (see below) as especially influential on him. In 1985 a position in the Princeton University Computer Center that required an advanced degree in Humanities and knowledge of computing became available; he took on the post while finishing his PhD dissertation and continuing to apply for tenure-track positions. Around this time he also began attending the ‘International Conference on Computers and the Humanities’ series and in this interview he describes some of the encounters that took place at those conferences and contributed to the formation of projects like TEI. As well as reflecting on his role in TEI he also compares and contrasts this experience with his work in W3C. On the whole, a somewhat ambivalent attitude towards his career emerges from the interview: he evokes Dorothy Sayers to communicate how the application of computers to the Humanities ‘overmastered’ him. Yet, he poignantly recalls how his first love was German Medieval languages and literature and the profound sense of loss he felt at not securing an academic post related to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Michael Sperberg-McQueen. (2018, March 3). In Wikipedia. Retrieved from https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Michael_Sperberg-McQueen&amp;amp;oldid=828576999&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michael Sperberg-McQueen</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 12 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s Probably the only Modestly Widely Used System with a Command Language in Latin: Manfred Thaller and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/manfred-thaller" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It’s Probably the only Modestly Widely Used System with a Command Language in Latin: Manfred Thaller and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2014-07-09T10:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-07-09T10:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/manfred-thaller</id><content type="html" xml:base="/manfred-thaller">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_13&quot;&gt;Chapter 13 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/admin/items/show/43&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview took place on 9 July 2014 at dh2014, the Digital Humanities Conference that was held in Lausanne, Switzerland that year. In it Thaller recalls that his earliest memory of encountering computing in the Humanities dates to c. 1973 when he attended a presentation on the use of computational techniques to map the spatial distribution of medieval coins. The difficulties of handling large, paper-based datasets was impressed upon him as he compiled some 32,000 index cards of excerpts for use in his PhD thesis. When he later encountered statistical standard software at the Institute for Advanced Studies in Vienna he found that such software could not be beneficially applied to historical data without first transforming in some way the historical data under study (indeed, the formalisation of historical and cultural heritage data is an issue that reoccurs in this interview, much as it did in Thaller’s research). In light of his experience of the problems of using such software ‘out of the box’ to work with historical data he went on to teach himself the programming language SNOBOL. Within a few weeks he had joined a project on daily life in the middle ages and was building software to manage the descriptions of images that the project compiled and stored on punched cards. Having contributed to various other projects with computational elements, in 1978 he took up a post at the Max Planck Institut for History in Göttingen. As well as discussing the research he carried out there, for example, CLIO/kλειω a databased programming system for History with a command language in Latin, he discusses the immense freedom and access to resources that he benefitted from. He also goes on to discuss some of the later projects he worked on, including those in the wider context of digital libraries, infrastructure and cultural heritage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Keynotes. (n.d.). Retrieved 20 June 2018, from https://dhd2015.uni-graz.at/de/nachlese/keynotes/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manfred Thaller</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 13 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry></feed>