<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-17T22:40:52+01:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Hidden Histories</title><subtitle>Digital Humanities 1949 - Present</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Hidden Histories</title><link href="/welcome" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Hidden Histories" /><published>2015-07-02T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-07-02T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="/welcome">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hidden Histories is a research project into the application of computational methods to the humanities during the period from 1949 to the present. The project conducts, collects and disseminates interviews with scholars and practitioners who were active during this period. Combining the interviews with archival data, new insight is gained into the emergence of a field known today as &lt;em&gt;digital humanities&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely accepted that the application of computational methods to the humanities can be traced back to at least 1949, when Roberto Busa envisaged an index variorum of some 11 million words of medieval Latin in the works of Thomas Aquinas and related authors. Notes and contributions towards a history of the computer in the humanities have appeared in recent years; however, our understanding of such developments remains incomplete and largely unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project gathers and makes available sources that enable the investigation of the social, intellectual and cultural context that shaped the earliest applications of computing to the humanities. It is from this context that the title ‘Hidden Histories’ derives because, for the most part, such information can not be gleaned from extant documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is interdisciplinary in its methodology and draws on oral history, digital humanities and cultural studies. With the aim of capturing memories, observations and insights that are rarely recorded in the scholarly literature of the field, the project conducts interviews with scholars and practitioners who applied computational methods to the humanities in the age of mainframe computing to the present day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An introduction to the Hidden Histories project is available as an &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqt044&quot;&gt;open access article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: “No. 0243,” Hidden Histories: Digital Humanities 1949 – Present, accessed June 17, 2018, http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/24.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Julianne Nyhan</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Hidden Histories is a research project into the application of computational methods to the humanities during the period from 1949 to the present. The project conducts, collects and disseminates interviews with scholars and practitioners who were active during this period. Combining the interviews with archival data, new insight is gained into the emergence of a field known today as digital humanities.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">They Took a Chance: Susan Hockey and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/susan-hockey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="They Took a Chance: Susan Hockey and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2013-06-21T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-06-21T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/susan-hockey</id><content type="html" xml:base="/susan-hockey">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2_6&quot;&gt;Chapter 6 of &lt;em&gt;Computation and the Humanities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;https://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/admin/items/show/44&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further related blog posts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archelogos.hypotheses.org/264&quot;&gt;related blog post&lt;/a&gt; written by Julianne Nyhan&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was carried out via Skype on 21 June 2013. Hockey was provided with the core questions in advance of the interview. Here she recalls how her interest in Humanities Computing was piqued by the articles that Andrew Morton published in the Observer in the 1960s about his work on the authorship of the Pauline Epistles. She went on to secure a position in the Atlas Computer Laboratory where she was an advisor on COCOA version 2 and wrote software for the electronic display of Arabic and other non-ASCII characters. The Atlas Computer Laboratory was funded by the Science Research Council and provided computing support for universities and researchers across the UK. While there she benefitted from access to the journal CHum and built connections with the emerging Humanities Computing community through events she attended starting with the ‘Symposium on Uses of the Computer in Literary Research’ organised by Roy Wisbey in Cambridge in 1970 (probably the earliest such meeting in the UK). Indeed, she emphasises the importance that such gatherings played in the formation of the discipline. As well as discussing her contribution to organisations like ALLC and TEI she recalls those who particularly influenced her such as, inter alia, Roberto Busa and Antonio Zampolli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Susan Hockey. (n.d.). Retrieved 16 June 2018, from http://www.chilton-computing.org.uk/acl/associates/permanent/hockey.htm&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Susan Hockey</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Chapter 6 of Computation and the Humanities</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Collaboration Must Be Fundamental or It’s Not Going to Work”: an Oral History Conversation between Harold Short and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/harold-short" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Collaboration Must Be Fundamental or It's Not Going to Work”: an Oral History Conversation between Harold Short and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2012-06-01T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-06-01T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/harold-short</id><content type="html" xml:base="/harold-short">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000133/000133.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000133/resources/audio/harold_short.MP3&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harold Short recounts that his interest in Computing and the Humanities goes back to when he was an undergraduate in English and French at a university in the former Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe). There, whilst undertaking summer work in the library, he saw first-hand the potential of digital methods. After arriving in London in 1972 he took an Open University degree in mathematics, computing and systems. Among his early influences he identifies the reading he did on matters related to cognitive science whilst undertaking a postgraduate certificated in education. In the UK he worked at the BBC as programmer, systems analyst and then systems manager. In 1988 he moved to King’s College London to take up the post of Assistant Director in Computing Services for Humanities and Information Management. One of his first tasks was to work with the Humanities Faculty to develop an undergraduate programme in humanities and computing. The first digital humanities conference he attended was the first joint international conference of ALLC and ACH, held at the University Toronto in 1989, which c. 450 people attended. He reflects on aspects of the institutional shape of the field towards the end of the 1980s, including the key Centres that existed then, the first meeting of the Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing (ALLC) and those who were active in it such as Roy Wisbey, Susan Hockey and the late Antonio Zampolli. He gives a detailed discussion of the development of what is now the Department of Digital Humanities in King’s College London, both in terms of the administrative and institutional issues involved, as well as the intellectual. He also reflects on some of the most successful collaborations that the Department has been involved in, for example, the AHRC funded Henry III Fine Rolls project, and the conditions and working practices that characterised them. He closes by discussing his impressions about the movement of scholars into and out of the discipline and of the institutional issues that have had an impact on digital humanities centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Harold Short - Research Portal, King’s College, London. (n.d.). Retrieved 17 June 2018, from https://kclpure.kcl.ac.uk/portal/en/persons/harold-short(0426328d-ff7b-4536-aeff-6cebdbebbecc).html&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harold Short</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Digital Humanities Quarterly</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trading Stories: an Oral History Conversation between Geoffrey Rockwell and Julianne Nyhan</title><link href="/geoffrey-rockwell" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trading Stories: an Oral History Conversation between Geoffrey Rockwell and Julianne Nyhan" /><published>2012-04-28T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-04-28T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/geoffrey-rockwell</id><content type="html" xml:base="/geoffrey-rockwell">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000135/000135.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000135/resources/audio/geoffrey_rockwell.MP3&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extended interview with Geoffrey Rockwell was carried out via Skype on the 28th April 2012. He narrates that he had been aware of computing developments when growing up in Italy but it was in college in the late 1970s that he took formal training in computing. He bought his first computer, an Apple II clone, after graduation when he was working as a teacher in the Middle East. Throughout the interview he reflects on the various computers he has used and how the mouse that he used with an early Macintosh instinctively appealed to him. By the mid-1980s he was attending graduate school in the University of Toronto and was accepted on to the Apple Research Partnership Programme, which enabled him to be embedded in the central University of Toronto Computing Services; he went on to hold a full time position there. Also taking a PhD in Philosophy, he spent many lunch times talking with John Bradley. This resulted in the building of text analysis tools and their application to Hume’s Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion, as well as some of the earliest, if not the earliest, conference paper on visualisation in the digital humanities community. He reflects on the wide range of influences that shaped and inspired his early work in the field, for example, the Research Computing Group at the University of Toronto and their work in visual programming environments. In 1994 he applied, and was hired at McMaster University to what he believes was the first job openly advertised as a humanities computing position in Canada. After exploring the opposition to computing that he encountered he reflects that the image of the underdog has perhaps become a foundational myth of digital humanities and questions whether it is still a useful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Advancing digital literacy in an era of big data | Work of Arts. (2017, July 10). Retrieved 16 June 2018, from https://www.woablog.com/2017/07/advancing-digital-literacy-in-an-era-of-big-data/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Digital Humanities Quarterly</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Questioning, Asking and Enduring Curiosity: an Oral History Conversation between Julianne Nyhan and Willard McCarty</title><link href="/willard-mccarty" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questioning, Asking and Enduring Curiosity: an Oral History Conversation between Julianne Nyhan and Willard McCarty" /><published>2012-03-27T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-03-27T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/willard-mccarty</id><content type="html" xml:base="/willard-mccarty">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full text: in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000134/000134.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio version: accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/3/000134/resources/audio/willard_mccarty.MP3&quot;&gt;audio interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was carried out with Willard McCarty on Tuesday 27th March, 2012 in University College London. He recounts that his earliest encounter with computing was in the Lawrence Radiation Laboratory in Berkley where he worked with semi-automated scanning equipment for the Alvarez high-energy physics projects. After his dreams of becoming a physicist were thwarted he transferred to Reed College. There he did not have the opportunity to take formal training in computing; for the most part, Computer Science departments did not exist then. So, he learned to programme “on the job” with help from a talented physicist turned computer programmer named Bill Gates (no association with Microsoft). His first encounter with what we now call digital humanities was at the University of Toronto where he worked on the Records of Early English Drama project whilst undertaking a PhD on 17th century non-dramatic poetry. In 1984/5, as he was finishing his PhD, he accepted an academic support role at the Centre for Computing in the Humanities at Toronto, where he remained until 1996 when he accepted an academic post in King’s College London. In Toronto he was keenly aware of the staff-faculty divide and the marginalised position of those who used computers in Humanities research. Nevertheless, the opportunities that the role brought to meet with a range of scholars interested in computing had a lasting influence on him. So too, with funding from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada he was able to undertake a research project on Ovid’s Metamorphosis. He closes the interview by reflecting on his early involvement with the conference scene and people who have influenced him, from academics to his calligraphy teacher Lloyd Reynolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo: Bern (2014, January 29). Retrieved 16 June 2018, from http://www.mccarty.org.uk/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>willard</name></author><category term="Oral History" /><summary type="html">Full text: in Digital Humanities Quarterly</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Podcasts of Symposium on Methodologies for the History of Computing in the Humanities, c.1949-1980 now available!</title><link href="/symposium-on-methodologies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podcasts of Symposium on Methodologies for the History of Computing in the Humanities, c.1949-1980 now available!" /><published>2011-09-17T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2011-09-17T11:18:00+01:00</updated><id>/symposium-on-methodologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="/symposium-on-methodologies">&lt;p&gt;University College London, 17 September 2011
(Sponsored by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hkfz.uni-trier.de/?&amp;amp;sel_id=1&quot;&gt;HKFZ&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/dh/&quot;&gt;UCLDH&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Click the titles to listen to the podcasts.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;opening-keynote--beyond-chronology-and-profession-discovering-how-to-write-a-history-of-the-digital-humanities&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/11&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opening Keynote&lt;/strong&gt; : Beyond chronology and profession: discovering how to write a history of the Digital Humanities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willard McCarty, Department of Digital Humanities, King’s College London; Centre for Cultural Research, University of Western Sydney.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;knowledge-spaces-and-digital-humanities&quot;&gt;Knowledge Spaces and Digital Humanities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claudine Moulin, Universitaet Trier, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unwriting-the-history-of-humanities-computing&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/10&quot;&gt;Unwriting the history of Humanities Computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Vanhoutte, Royal Academy of Dutch Language and Literature - Ghent, Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;crowd-sourcing-beyond-the-traditional-boundaries-of-academic-history&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/9&quot;&gt;Crowd sourcing: beyond the traditional, boundaries of academic history&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Melissa Terras, Dept. Information Studies, UCL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;different-stories-to-be-lived-and-told-recovering-lehmann-james-oppenheimer-1868-1916-for-the-narrative-of-the-irish-arts--crafts-movement-1894-1925&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/12&quot;&gt;Different stories to be lived and told: recovering Lehmann James Oppenheimer (1868-1916) for the narrative of the Irish Arts &amp;amp; Crafts movement (1894-1925)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James G.R. Cronin, School of History &amp;amp; Centre for Adult Continuing Education, University College Cork, Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;oral-history-and-acts-of-recovery-humanizing-history&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/6&quot;&gt;Oral History and acts of recovery: humanizing history?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Flinn, Dept. Information Studies, UCL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lost-origins-of-information-science&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/7&quot;&gt;Lost origins of Information Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanda Broughton, Dept. Information Studies, UCL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dh-pioneers-and-progeny-some-reflections-on-generational-accomplishment-and-engagement-in-the-digital-humanities&quot;&gt;DH pioneers and progeny: some reflections on generational accomplishment and engagement in the Digital Humanities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray Siemens, Faculty of Humanities, University of Victoria. (Virtual presentation)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;closing-keynote-data-vs-text-forty-years-of-confrontation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hiddenhistories.omeka.net/items/show/8&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Closing Keynote&lt;/strong&gt;: Data vs. Text: forty years of confrontation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lou Burnard, Oxford University Computing Services (Emeritus).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;discussion-towards-an-oral-history-of-computing-in-the-humanities-chaired-by-anne-welsh-and-julianne-nyhan-dept-information-studies-ucl&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion&lt;/strong&gt;: towards an oral history of Computing in the Humanities, Chaired by Anne Welsh and Julianne Nyhan, Dept. Information Studies, UCL&lt;/h4&gt;</content><author><name>Julianne Nyhan</name></author><category term="activities" /><category term="talks" /><summary type="html">University College London, 17 September 2011 (Sponsored by HKFZ and UCLDH)</summary></entry></feed>